<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The fruits of a fast, appointed by the churches gathered against Christ and his kingdom, who go about to mock God with their outside-worship, and appointed fasts, and dayes of voluntary humiliation. Or, A declaration of the persecution of a messenger of the Lord, by a people who go under the name of Independants, in Essex, who have set themselves in the enmity of their spirits to oppose the truth of God, calling it a lye, and persecuting his messengers as deceivers, and wanderers, wherein their persecuting spirits is made manifest, and them to be in Cains generation, and stranges to the spirit of Christ, which vener persecuted, and so are noen of his, Rom.8:9. And also, of the unjust dealing of Judge Hills, ... And also, severall queries, that was sent ot the priests and magistrates, shich may be serviceable for them, or any other to answer, whom they do concern. / By ... James Parnell.</title>
            <author>Parnell, James, 1637?-1656.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 93 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91466</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P530</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E854_14</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207483</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866532</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866532</idno>
            <idno type="VID">168328</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91466)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 168328)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 129:E854[14])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The fruits of a fast, appointed by the churches gathered against Christ and his kingdom, who go about to mock God with their outside-worship, and appointed fasts, and dayes of voluntary humiliation. Or, A declaration of the persecution of a messenger of the Lord, by a people who go under the name of Independants, in Essex, who have set themselves in the enmity of their spirits to oppose the truth of God, calling it a lye, and persecuting his messengers as deceivers, and wanderers, wherein their persecuting spirits is made manifest, and them to be in Cains generation, and stranges to the spirit of Christ, which vener persecuted, and so are noen of his, Rom.8:9. And also, of the unjust dealing of Judge Hills, ... And also, severall queries, that was sent ot the priests and magistrates, shich may be serviceable for them, or any other to answer, whom they do concern. / By ... James Parnell.</title>
                  <author>Parnell, James, 1637?-1656.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert, and are to be sold at his shop, at the Black-spread-Eagle, neer the West-end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Octob: 19. 1655".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:168328:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE FRVITS OF A FAST, Appointed by the Churches gathered againſt Chriſt and his Kingdom, who go about to mock God with their outſide-Worſhip, and appointed Faſts, and Dayes of Voluntary Humiliation.</p>
            <p>Or, A Declaration of the perſecution of a Meſſenger of the Lord, by a people who go under the name of Independants, in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> who have ſet themſelves in the enmity of their Spirits to oppoſe the Truth of God, calling it a lye, and perſecuting his Meſſengers as Decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, and Wanderers, wherein their perſecuting Spirits is made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, and them to be in <hi>Cains</hi> Generation, and ſtrangers to the Spirit of Chriſt, which never perſecuted, and ſo are none of his, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.9.</p>
            <p>And alſo, of the unjuſt dealings of Judge <hi>Hills,</hi> who ſate upon life and death at the laſt Aſſizes, at <hi>Chansford,</hi> which began upon the eleventh day of the ſixth month.</p>
            <p>And alſo, Severall queries, that was ſent to the Prieſts and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, which may be ſerviceable for them, or any other to Anſwer, whom they do concern.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By a VVitneſs, and ſufferer in outward Bonds, for the unchangeable Truth of God, by</hi> Cains <hi>Generation, who am known to them (by the name) in</hi> Colcheſter Caſtle, JAMES PARNELL.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop, at the Black-ſpread-Eagle neer the Weſt-end of <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1655.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:168328:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:168328:2"/>
            <head>THE FRUITS OF A FAST, appointed by the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches gathered againſt Chriſt and his Kingdome, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>IRST, I ſhall give unto the Reader, <hi>a declaration of the work of God in my Soul,</hi> and the converſion of my heart from dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs unto his marvelous Light, and from the power of Satan unto God, and out of the path of death into the path of Life, where I now walk in the Light of my God, with the Ranſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of the Lord, who are travelling towards the Holy City; and alſo the cauſe of my coming forth into the World to declare the truth, for which I now ſuffer Bonds, by the perſecuting Generation, wherein I once lived a Child of wrath (as all are by nature) and when I was loved of the world, while I followed the vain courſes and wayes of the world, where by nature I was led in imitation of others, being in that nature which is prone unto the ſame: the time I was ſent unto the Schools of humane learning, for to learn the humane wiſdome, for which end the Schooles are profitable; but for the attaining of heavenly wiſdom and knowledg, they are as far unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, and many bookes that are there read, are much for the corrupting of youth, and the nouriſhing of the wild prophane nature, which then ruled in me, and I was as wild as others, during the time I followed the School; and after I was taken from the School, I ſtil continued in the ſame nature, growing and encreaſing in ſin and iniquity, following the vain courſes of the wicked world, &amp; alſo was trayned up in the cuſtomary way of the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the world, which is held in the Idols Temple, every firſt day of the week, but no converſion there was wrought, but all ſtill continued in the old nature, both Prieſt and people, young and old, and as was the people, ſo
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:168328:3"/>was the Prieſt, all walking in darkneſs and blindneſs, by form, cuſtome<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and tradition, but ignorant of the pure light, which is the guide and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher of the faithful, which oftentimes did reprove in ſecret, when I was a lone, but then I knew not what it was, but oftentimes it did ſtrike me into a conſideration of my wayes and doings, and ſet life and death before me, ſo that I have ſometimes promiſed within my ſelf, never to do the like again, but the promiſe being<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in the wil made, it did not ſtand, but when the temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations came, the careleſs mind got out again, and led me ſtill to delight my heart in the vanity which my eye did ſee, and my ear did hear, which all paſſed away with the uſing thereof, and left me to the judgement which was due unto me, for my iniquity, which did follow me time after time, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling me to repentance, and the more I did incline my mind and draw nigh to it, it alſo did draw nigh to me, and ſo the goodneſs of God led me to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and the Grace of God wrought in my heart a Reformation, and ſo I was found of him when I ſought not; and thus he both wrought the will and the deed of his own good pleaſure, and plucked me as a brand out of the fire, to make me a veſſel of honor to his name; all living eretnal pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, be to his name for ever; my ſoul ſhall praiſe and magnifie his name for ever; For, I may wel ſay with <hi>Paul, Of ſinners<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I was chiefe;</hi> for according to my years, J was as perfect in ſin and iniquity, as any in the Town where I lived; yea, and exceeded many in the ſame, ſo that there was as little hopes of my converſion, as any in the Town; and yet though it is a place of many people, J was the firſt in all that town which the Lord was pleaſed to make known his power in, and turn my heart towards him, and truly to ſeek him, ſo that J became a wonder to the World, and an aſtoniſhment to the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then round about, but they was ſuch enemies to goodneſs, and ſo given up to idolatry, that as much as before they had loved me in my vain conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, ſo much the more thdy hated me in my converſion, yea, and my Families came to inſnare me, and lay wait for me for to intrap me, but when they could not prevaile,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 41.9.</note> they ſtood afar of me, and reproached me with lyes, and proved my greateſt enemies, yea, and my Relations became my adverſaries, and laboured to deſtroy what God had began in me, becauſe that thereby J came under the reproach and ſhame of the world, becauſe J could not conform to the world in their invented facious cuſtomes and traditions, and their words, wayes, fellowſhip, and worſhip, but was made ſubject to the law of God, and could not reſpect perſons, neither in word nor deed; then the beaſt which rules in proud fleſh was diſturbed, who before ruled in peace while he was worſhipped; but when I came to ſee proud Lucifer,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.38.</note> the luſt in man, to be the beaſt, which all the world worſhips and wanders after, but theſe whoſe names are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the book of life; therefore J could no longer follow the world in blindneſs, for by the power of God my eye was opened, ſo that J did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold their idolatry, and therefore J could no longer be conformable to them, ſo that their rage and perſecution aroſe againſt me, and J became a
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:168328:3"/>mock in the ſtreets; yea, and was I accounted as one not worthy to live a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them; yea, and they ſaid, he that killed me would do God ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; but he that had called me out from amongſt them unto himſelf, that I might no longer follow the vain courſes of the world, nor ſet my delight no things below, but that I might ſerve him in newneſs of life, that in me his workmanſhip might appear, to the confounding of the heathen, who know him not; he by his power kept me, and gave me ſtrength to bear his Croſs, and deſpiſe the ſhame; ſo that neither foul words nor faire words, could cauſe me to deny what God by his grace had wrought in my heart, but by his power he carryed me above the raging waves of the tempeſtuous ſea, ſo that I knew that he that was in me, was greater than he that is in the world; yea, and out of my kinred and acquaintance I came, and became a ſtranger to them that loved not the truth; yea, and preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I came to ſee the Prieſts of the world, by their fruits, and the fruits of their Miniſtry, which was curſed from God, and therefore profited not the people at all; but when the Lord by his power had changed and converted my heart unto himſelf, the Prieſts became mine enemies, and ſaid I was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded, whenas before, when I lived in the vain converſation of the world, they took no notice of me, either to reprove me or inſtruct me, but as they went on in a cuſtomary way, for again and lucre, ſpeaking againſt ſin in the generall but not reproving it in particular, but was as deep in it in their lives as others, and ſo what they preached down with their tongues they upheld in their lives, and countenanced in their converſations, and ſo from them I turned, whom I ſaw had gotten a form, but denyed the life and power, and I ſought for a people with whom I might have union; and there was a people with whom I found union, a few miles from the Town where I lived, whom the Lord was a gathering out of the dark world, to ſit down together and wait upon his name, but we was the objects and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of the countrey, and was accounted as the off-ſcourings of the world but in all this we ſaw the Scriptures fulfilled, and that we might thus ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer if we would live godly in Chriſt Jeſus,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.12.</note> and here was our confidence and ſtrength, which carryed us above our ſufferings, as knowing it greater riches to ſuffer affliction with the people of God, than to enjoy the pleaſures of ſin for a ſeaſon; and about this time I was about 15 years of age, &amp; afterwards I was called forth to viſit ſome friends in the North part of England, with whom I had union in ſpirit before I ſaw their faces, and afterwards I retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned back to my outward dwelling place, and remained in my outward cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and the Lord all this time ſtil more and more perfecting and encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his work in my heart, which by his power he had begun in me, &amp; by his pure power bringing forth his truth in me, and making known his wil unto me, until by his power he opened my mouth to declare his truth in the world, &amp; ſtil I continued in my outward calling, and alſo in the work of the Lord, as not being called far from my dwelling place, and when I was
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:168328:4"/>betwixt 17. and 18. years of age, I was moved in my ſpirit to go to a place about fifteen miles from my outward dwelling place (ſouthward) amongſt a people, to whom the Lord was making known his truth, not knowing when I went out of going farther than that place; but when I was there, I was moved of the Lord to come on to <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and in obedience unto the Lord, I came to ſee what he had to do for me, not knowing one ſoot of the way, but as I was directed, neither knowing when I came there where to be received, but had heard before of two of my friends that was there whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, cauſed by the Mayor that then was, onely for declaring the truth as they paſt through the town, againſt the deceipt thereof, neither did I know but it might be my portion alſo when I came there; but without conferring with fleſh and blood, I paſſed on my journey, and he that called me forth went along with me, and did direct me, and when I came there, I found theſe that was worthy that received me; and alſo I found a friend, whom the corrupt Rulers had put in priſon for the ſame teſtimony which I alſo was ſent to declare; and before I had continued there the ſpace of fourteen nights, <hi>VVilliam Pickering</hi> the Mayor of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> committed me to Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for publiſhing two Papers, the one againſt the corruption of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, and the other againſt the corruption of the Prieſts, at the time of their commencement, as they call it, and there they kept me in Priſon the ſpace of two Seſſions, and toſſed me from Priſon to Dungeon, and had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to lay againſt me, whereby to prove the breach of any Law, but when I came to the laſt Seſſions, they called a Jury to prove the Papers to be ſcandalous and ſeditious Papers, and they was nigh two hours about them but could not prove it, but came and ſaid that they found nothing, but that the Papers was mine, which I had before owned in the open Court, and there was my name to them to teſtifie the ſame; and ſo they was croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in their intentions, and their plots came to nought: then they commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted me back to Priſon again, and after the ſpace of three dayes they ſent me away with a Paſſe, under the name of a Rogue, yet durſt not give me the Law which belongs to Rogues, but had me away with Clubs and Staves, and I could not ſee the Paſs until I was three miles out of the town where I lodged that night, and the next day there came a Juſtice of peace from <hi>Cambridge,</hi> who knowing me to be innocent of what was laid to my charge, ſo he witneſſed the Paſſe to be falſe, and took it back to <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and ſo I was ſet free: And not long after <hi>I</hi> went to <hi>Cambridge,</hi> again, and went abroad, preaching and declaring the truth freely in the Countries about, and many <hi>I</hi> found that received the truth gladly, but more ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; yet nevertheleſs, Truth ſpread and conquered over its enemies; &amp; there I continued labouring in the work of the Lord about the ſpace of halfe a year in the Countries about <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and from thence I was moved of the Lord to come into <hi>Eſſex,</hi> where I heard of the people that was ſeeking the Lord, and when I came there, I found thoſe that were worthy, who received the truth gladly, and there I continued, freely declaring and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:168328:4"/>preaching the truth, from place to place, ſometimes in the Synagogues and was haled out by the Prieſts party, that the Scripture might be fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led upon that Generation; yet nevertheleſs, I continued in conſtant prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the word to the conſciences of the people, freely and publickly, in ſeverall plains of the Countrey, notwithſtanding much oppoſition both of Prieſts, people, and profeſſors, and much did the truth prevail in the hearts of people, to the glory of God the father of truth, which did make glad the hearts of many, who have long expected this day to appear; but the falſe Prophet begun to utter forth his lyes and Blaſphemies againſt the truth, and the Beaſt (by whoſe power the falſe Prophet ſtands) began to rage and perſecute; and the Miniſters of Antichriſt ſtood up for their Kingdome, crying againſt truth, ſtriving to preſent it odious in the ears of the people, but when J came to their faces, they fled like hirelings, and left their I lock behind, ſo that the truth much prevailed, notwithſtanding their railing and raging, ſo that they begun to appoint meetings, purpoſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſet themſelves againſt the truth, to preſent it to the people, as error and hereſie, ſo that if by any means they could by their evil incenſing and leavening of the minds of the people, turn away their mindes from heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the truth; and on the other ſide they had the earthly powers to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold them and ſtrengthen them againſt whomſoever ſhould come to gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay them, and to lay their Law upon them; ſo I hearing of a publick Mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that was appointed by the Prieſts and Profeſſors of theſe times, to be at a Town, called <hi>Great Coggaſhall</hi> upon the 12. day of the 5th. month, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Luly,</hi> as was declared in publike by the Prieſt of the ſaid Town, to Faſt and pray againſt the errors (as they ſaid) of the people called Quakers, and alſo their intent was to inſnare me, and to bring my body into Bonds if that <hi>I</hi> came amongſt them for to defend the truth, which afterward ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, and although I did ſee their intent towards me, <hi>I</hi> was made wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling not only to be bound, but alſo to ſuffer for the pure eternal Truth which <hi>I</hi> am made a witneſs of, ſo <hi>I</hi> being preſſed in my ſpirit for to go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, and in obedience to the ſame <hi>I</hi> went, and there was one Prieſt <hi>VVillis,</hi> an independant Teacher, who was ſet up in the ſeat of the Phariſee, the chiefeſt place of the Aſſembly,<note place="margin">Mat. 23.6</note> theſe ſpeaking a divination of his own Brain, and not from the Mouth of the Lord, and therefore knew not how to divide the Word aright, but cryed againſt falſe Prophets, and Deceivers, and he himſelf one of them; and when the Prieſt had done, I ſpoke unto the people, in vindication of the truth of God, which the Prieſt had before reproached, reviled, and blaſphemed, but the Prieſts and the Rulers interrupted me, and run into many words, which bred much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order and confuſion; and then another of the Prieſts got up into the Pulpet, and they bid me put off my hat, and ſtand with my hat off the time the Prieſts was praying, which worſhip <hi>I</hi> denyed, and therefore could not be conformable to it, and ſo J ſaid, before J ſhould be ſubject to their wills, J would paſſe out of the meeting place, and ſo J did, and many people
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:168328:5"/>came out after me, for I intended to declare the truth in the Town, being I could not have liberty in the publick place; and as I was paſſing on the way quietly towards my friends houſe, he that is called Juſtice <hi>VVakering</hi> came ruſhing behind me amongſt the people, and ſuddenly ſmote me with his hand upon my back, and ſaid, he arreſted me in the name of the Lord Protector, and ſo I turned me about, and looked upon him, (but knew not that he was a Magiſtrate) ſo I asked him, where was his writ? and hee ſaid, he had one, but none he ſhewed me; then they hurried me into a houſe and there ſome friends ingaged that I ſhould be forth-coming when their worſhip was done; and ſo I went unto my friends houſe, and there ſpoke the word of the Lord unto the people that there came together, and was alſo ready when their worſhip was done, according to my friends ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and when I came before them, there was four men called Juſtices, and ſix or ſeven Prieſts; yea, there was nigh nine or ten Prieſts that day, that was gathered together againſt the truth; and when I was come before them, he that is called Iuſtice <hi>VVakering,</hi> came and plucked my hat off my head, and threw it away; then they fel to queſtion me of many things, to which I made anſwer, and many frivolous queſtions they asked mee, whereby to inſnare me, which was neither juſt nor honeſt for men of their profeſſion to do; ſo when they had ſatisfied their wills in examining of me, they cauſed a <hi>Mittimus</hi> to be made, and committed me to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Goal at <hi>Colcheſter,</hi> and there was ſeveral of the chief Prieſts in <hi>Eſſex</hi> that was actors in this Perſecution; Prieſt <hi>VVillis,</hi> who is a Teacher of an Independant company at <hi>Brantry,</hi> and Prieſt <hi>Sammes,</hi> a Teacher of an Independant company at Great <hi>Coggaſhal,</hi> and Prieſt <hi>Sparrow,</hi> a Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher of an Independant company at <hi>Halſtead,</hi> and Prieſt <hi>Stellum</hi> a Teacher of an Independant company at <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ling,</hi> yet are all Pariſh Prieſts, and are maintained by thoſe that are not of their Church, and thoſe was the head actors in this perſecution; yea, and Prieſt <hi>Stellum</hi> ſpoke to the Rulers in the publike place, thereby to ſtir up their ſpirits to perſecute; and this was plotted amongſt the Prieſts and their gathered Churches, to appoint mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.15 16.</note> thereby to inſnare the innocent, and raiſe perſecution againſt the truth; yea, and two of the men called Juſrices, who was my chief perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, are members of the Independant Church; and thus the Churches garher themſelves againſt Chriſt and his Kingdome; and now the ravening wolves in ſheeps clothing doth appear, yea their fruits makes them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, and thoſe are they which calls themſelves Iews and are not, but the Synagogue of Satan, and thoſe are the builders which have and do reject the Corner-ſtone, which is now become the head of the Corner, and over their heads is ſet, and woe unto them on whom it lights. And after I was ſent to priſon, there I was kept cloſe, and could not have my friends and acquaintance to come to ſee me with peace and freedome; and ſo when I was there, I writ an Anſwer to the <hi>Mittimus,</hi> whereby I was falſly accuſed and impriſoned, and ſent to the men that committed me, for to clear my
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:168328:5"/>conſcience unto them, &amp; lay their injuſtice &amp; cruelty before them, &amp; leave them without excuſe in the preſence of the almighty; &amp; ſo when the time came that I was to go to the Aſſize, they put me on a chain amongſt felons and Murderers, and joyned me to one ſuſpected for murder; and thus I was numbred amongſt tranſgreſſors, that the Scripture might be fulfilled, and thus ſix of us was hooked together upon a Chain, ſo that we could not go into a bed, for four of us remained upon the Chain day and night, and thus I was led 18. miles through the Countrey for a gazing-ſtock unto the world; but truth was preached in all this, and prevailed on the hearts of the people, ſo that I could rejoyce in all, and triumph over mine enemies: So when we was at the Aſſize Town, which is called <hi>Chansford,</hi> the Juge came in upon the ſeventh day of the week, and upon the ſecond day of the next week I was brought into the Court before Judge <hi>Hills,</hi> who ſate upon life and death, and there I ſtood for a gazing-ſtock a while, and then the Judg commanded them to take me away, and did not ſay any thing to me, for then I was ſingled from the reſt, onely had Irons upon one of my hands, then upon the next day morning the Goaler ſent his man to take off my o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Irons, and ſo in the afternoon I was had before the Judge without any Irons, and the Goaler took off my hat and caſt it upon the floore, and then the Clerk read a long Indictment full of falſehoods, and asked me if I was guilty, and I told him I denyed all guilt, and called for my accuſers, and the Judge ſaid I might ſee my accuſers, and told me I might ſay guilty or not guilty, and I told him I was not guilty; ſo they called twelve men to try me, and the Foreman was a drunkard, and they bid me object againſt any of them, and <hi>I</hi> told them I owned none out of the doctrine of Chriſt, and all that ſwore was out of the Doctrine of Chriſt, and they had all ſworn before my face, and therefore I openly denyed by them to be tryed; yet nevertheleſs they went on with their work, and Prieſt <hi>VVillis</hi> was called and he ſwore againſt me, and ſwore falſly too; and the two men called Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices ſwore againſt me, and ſwore falſly too; and one of the Juſtices m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> (ſo called,) and another man ſwore againſt me, and ſwore falſly too; yet all theſe falſe witneſſes was heard to the full what they would ſay againſt me, and thus the leader of the people cauſed them to erre, for if the tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher be a ſwearer and a falſe ſwearer, what may the people be? for Chriſt ſaith, ſwear not at all, but let your yea, be yea, and your nay be nay, for whatſoever is more is evil: and the Apoſtle ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.34.35, 36, 37 <hi>Iam.</hi> 5.12. 2 <hi>Iohn</hi> 9.</note> in all things my bre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thren ſwear not at all, <hi>&amp;c,</hi> and he that abides not in the Doctrine of Chriſt hath not God; and thus like people like Prieſt, all live without God in the world. And when their falſe witneſſes had ſpoken what they could againſt me, they brought in the Letter which I had ſent to the men called Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in Reply to their Mittimus, and it was openly read in the COURT, and I owned it, for my Name was to it, and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of it was much ſatisfaction to many that underſtood it,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:168328:6"/>and they alſo brought another Paper that I writ againſt the Idols Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and the deceiver therein; both which ſhall follow in order afterward; and then when they were both read, <hi>Iudge Hilles</hi> took them both, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated over unto the <hi>Iury</hi> all that the could gather by wrong interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and conſtruction againſt me, whereby to incenſe the Jury againſt me, and told them if they did not find me guilty, the ſin would lye upon their heads, and he as it were paſſed the ſentence upon me before the Jury went forth, yea, and told them what they ſhould do, whenas they had ſworn be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to ſpeak the truth, and nothing but the truth, and I had charged them to take heed what they did, for I told them none could judge betwixt truth and hereſie, but by the ſpirit of the Lord; but when I would have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſomthing to the Jury before they went forth, the Judge interrupted me, and would not ſuffer me (though one of the Jury deſired it) neither would he ſuffer that the Jury ſhould have the papers that was brought in againſt me, though I required it, but ſought all that he could againſt me, true or falſe, although I had ſent him a true declaration of the grounds of my impriſonment, with the hands of four Witneſſes to it, neither would he ſuffer that to be read; and that which I would have ſpoken unto the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, was to clear it unto them, that it was no ſcandalous nor reproachfull words, to call a corrupt Magiſtrate, a corrupt Magiſtrate; and to call an unjuſt Judge and Lawyer, an unjuſt Judge and Lawyer; or a perſecutor, a perſecutor; or a deceiver, a deceiver; all which was brought againſt me, and called railing and ſcandalous, for by that account they might have taxed all the Prophets for railing and ſcandaling, for they open and often declared againſt the corruption of the Prieſts and Rulers, as you may read in many places in the Prophets Records, <hi>Iſajah</hi> called the Prieſts, greedy dumb dogs;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56.11. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34. <hi>Iohn</hi> 10. <hi>Lu.</hi> 13, 14, 15. <hi>Luke</hi> 13.31, 32. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.14.</note> and the Prophets called them Idoll-ſhepheards, and the like, and Chriſt called them hirelings, and Chriſt called the Rulers hypocrites, and <hi>Herod</hi> a Fox: and read the 23. of <hi>Matthew,</hi> and ſee if you may not as wel call that railing, and yet in all this they did not raile nor ſcandalize any, but gave to every nature its name, and due reproofe, whether they would hear or forbear; but this is the condemnation of the world, light is come into the world, and men love darkneſs rather than light, becauſe their deeds are evil. So when the Jury came into bring in their evidence; they could charge me with nothing, but the Paper I had writ in reply to my Mittimus after I was impriſoned, which Paper I had before owned in the open Court, with my name to it; but the Indictment they could not charge me with, for it tended to a Riot, which I was far from, or any that owned me, but the Judge and the Clerk, both, diſhoneſtly ſtrove to draw words out of the Fore-man of the Jury, which the reſt did not conſent to, neither could he ſpeak their minds, but others of the Jury was fain to ſpeak themſelves, but nothing was cleared againſt me, then the Goaler was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to take me away, &amp; when I was gone forth of the Court, they ſent for me again, and the Judge impoſed two fines upon me to the value of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:168328:6"/>about forty pounds, the one he ſaid was for the contempt of the Magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, the other for the contempt of the Miniſtry; for he ſaid, the Lord PROTECTOR had charged him to ſee to puniſh ſuch perſons, as ſhould contemn either Magiſtracy or Miniſtry: But what a Miniſtry is this, that ſtands in need of an outward Magiſtracy, to uphold it againſt a people that comes with nothing but ſpiritual weapons, to defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves againſt ſpiritual wickedneſs, which now ſits in high places; but this Miniſtry is contrary to the Miniſtry of Chriſt, whoſe weapons are not carnal but ſpiritual; and alſo ſeveral of mine accuſers ſtood upon the Bench hard by the Judge, ſeveral times whiſpering of him in the eare,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4.</note> and leavening and incenſing his minde againſt me and I reproved one of them in the open Court for ſo doing, and yet theſe things was ſuffered, and alſo the Judge gave charge unto the Goaler to let no giddy-headed people come to me (as he called them) which I never deſired that any ſuch ſhould come, but thereby they take occaſion to keep my friends from me, accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them giddy-headed people, but they are not giddy-headed people that own ſound Doctrine, but they are giddy-headed people that cannot indure ſound Doctrine, but have itching ears carried about with reports and hear-ſays, to ſpeak evil of the things they know not. But thus without all honeſty they acted in the enmity of their ſpirits againſt me, yet in all I was made to rejoyce, for I ſee their deceit was manifeſt to the people, and the Truth owned in many hearts, ſo that my ſufferings was not grievous but joyous; but as the Judges dealings was rigorous and unjuſt towards me, it was ſo much the more on the contrary to <hi>Barrabas,</hi> for there was three or four arraigned for ſuſpicion of <hi>Murder,</hi> and others for <hi>Felony,</hi> yet he did deliver them, and there was not one that dyed or was bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, neither which I did deſire, but onely this I do declare, to ſhew <hi>how the world loves its own,</hi> and how the ſame ſpirit now rules in both Prieſt, people, and Rulers, that ruled amongſt the <hi>Iewes,</hi> who eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Barrabas</hi> above <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>numbred him amongſt Tranſgreſſors;</hi> and ſo in all this the Scripture is fulfilled,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.12.</note> and the day further appears to the <hi>Glory of God, the Father of Truth,</hi> who wil <hi>exalt his truth by his own Power, over the heads of all its enemies:</hi> So then they brought me back to priſon again, where I ſtil remain in the <hi>peace and freedome of my ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> which none can take away, though in the hands of mine <hi>Enemies;</hi> yet this I know, <hi>That the inviſible God is working in ſecret by his power, and with a ſtrong arme, carrying on this great worke which hee hath begun in the Earth; yea, and he will bring down, and overturn all, untill it come into his hand whoſe owne it is, and hee will exalt his Kingdome in the hearts of his people, and his Son ſhal rule ovre the earth, yea, and all his Enemies ſhall be his footſtool, and ſhall bow unto him, and bee glad to lay downe their crownes before him, and acknowledge his power, yea, and he wil daſh all the forms and falſe likeneſses and images, which is ſet up by man in his imaginations, (calling them Churches;) and he will daſh them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:168328:7"/>Powers of the earth in pieces one againſt another, like a Potters Veſſel, though now they ſet at nought the Corner-ſtone, yet then by it ſhall they be grownd to powder, for our God is a conſuming fire, and who is able to ſtand in the day of his wrath? Therefore it is a fearful thing to fall into the hands of the living God, then woe to all his enemies, or he that lifts up his hand against his Maker, to contrary what he hath decreed.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="reply">
                        <head>Here followeth a Reply to my <hi>Mittimus,</hi> which was adjudged a contempt of the Magiſtracy.</head>
                        <p>VVHereas I who am of the World called <hi>James Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell,</hi> am committed as priſoner to bee kept in the Common-Goal, by a <hi>Mittimus</hi> ſealed and ſigned by you four men who are called Juſtices of the Peace, who write your ſelves <hi>Herbert Pellham, Thomas Cook, Dyoniſius Wakering, William Harlackinden,</hi> wherein I finde ſeverall Lyes, Slanders, and falſe Accuſations caſt upon me, therefore for the Truths ſake, and for the ſatisfaction of the ſimple, <hi>I</hi> ſhall reply to the ſame, and cleare the truth, and return the venome upon your venomous ſpirits from whence it comes, that you may bee convinced of your evill, and ceaſe fighting againſt Chriſt and his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
                        <div type="mittimus">
                           <head>Firſt your own, as followeth.</head>
                           <p>VVHereas it duly appears unto Us, by our own view, and alſo by the Examination of <hi>James Parnell,</hi> who ſaith, he was borne at <hi>Retford,</hi> in the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:168328:7"/>County of <hi>Nottingham,</hi> Labourer, that he the ſaid <hi>James Parnell,</hi> with very many other perſons of his gathering together, did this day in a riotous man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner enter into the Pariſh Church at Great <hi>Coggaſhal</hi> aforeſaid, and there being a great number of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans met in the ſaid Church, to hold and keep a day of Publike humiliation, and ſeeking of God, and being in order thereunto then exerciſed in the Divine Worſhip and Service of God Almighty, hoe the ſaid <hi>James</hi> did then and there ſtand up, and told the Miniſter blaſphemed, and ſpoke falſly, and uſed many other reproachfull words againſt the ſaid Miniſter, and afterward hee departed the ſaid Church, and went into the Common High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, in the ſaid Towne of Great <hi>Coggaſhall,</hi> with a great number of perſons his followers, who kept there unlawfully together, and ſome of them gave out menacing and threatning ſpeeches, tending to the breach of the Peace, and againſt the Law; and alſo the ſaid <hi>James</hi> cannot give us a very good account where he was laſt ſetled, or of his life and converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but doth further appear unto us to bee an idle, diſorderly perſon: Theſe are therefore in the Name of his Highneſs the Lord Protector, to will and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire you to convey forthwith the ſaid <hi>James Parnell,</hi> unto the Common-Goale for this COUNTY, there to remaine untill the next Generall Goale-Delivery to be holden for this COUNTY, and until thence de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered by due courſe of Law, unleſs he the ſaid <hi>James</hi> ſhal come before us, or any two of us, or two ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Juſtices of the Peace for this COUNTY, and ſhall finde very able and ſufficient Sureties to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:168328:8"/>be bound with him by Recognizance for his perſonal appearance at the ſaid next Goale-Delivery, there to anſwer what ſhal bee then objected againſt him, and not to depart thence without licenſe of the Court, and in the mean time to bee of good behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, and thereof faile not at your peril. Dated at <hi>Coggaſhal</hi> aforeſaid, the twelfth day of <hi>Iuly,</hi> 1655. The Keeper of the ſaid Common-Goale is hereby required to receive and keep the ſaid <hi>Iames,</hi> if hee ſhall be brought unto him.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>
                                 <list>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Herbert Pellham,</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Thomas Cook,</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Dyoniſius Wakering,</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>William Harlackinden.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                 </list>
                              </signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                        <div type="text">
                           <pb n="13" facs="tcp:168328:8"/>
                           <head>A Reply to the aforeſaid Mittimus.</head>
                           <div n="1" type="accusation">
                              <p>WHereas I am hereby accuſed, that I (who am of the World called <hi>IAMES PARNELL</hi>) with very many other Perſons of my gathering together, did this day in a Riotous manner, enter the Pariſh Church of <hi>Great Coggaſhall,</hi> afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid.</p>
                              <div type="reply">
                                 <head>Reply.</head>
                                 <p>ARe you not aſhamed, who profeſs your ſelves Miniſters of law, ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and peace, to begin with lyes and make them your refuge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the innocent, tending to the diſturbance of the peace of the faithfull, whom you both ought and would encourage and countenance, if you were faithfull Miniſters of peace and juſtice, ſtanding in the pure coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of God, ruling for God and not for your ſelves, in all things diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging your conſciences unto God without partiallity, or reſpect of perſons, as faithfull Miniſters of Law and Juſtice; but contrary unto this you have acted in your corrupt wills, turning your ſwords againſt the meſſengers of the moſt High, and wilfully reſiſting the truth of God, making lyes your refuge, as here doth plainly appear; for upon the day aforeſaid, I was at a friends houſe in <hi>Great Coggaſhall,</hi> where ſeverall friends and neighbours was come to ſee me, and there ſate peaceably together, waiting upon the Lord; and I having heard of a publick meeting at the Steeplehouſe in the ſaid town, of the Prieſts and Profeſſors of theſe times, as it was openly pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by Prieſt <hi>Sammes,</hi> and the Prieſt of the ſaid Town, in the ſaid Stee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plehouſe, upon the firſt day laſt paſt, to that end as I heard, and ſince did underſtand, for to faſt and pray againſt (and lay open the errors, as they ſaid) of the people called Quakers, for the returning of them who owned them, and the eſtabliſhing &amp; ſtrengthning thoſe againſt them that did not own them (to wit) the people called quakers; ſo I being preſſed in my ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit for to go amongſt them, in the behalf and defence of the truth of God, brought forth in theſe people whom the world ſcornfully calls <hi>Quakers,</hi> I alſo being made a Miniſter of the ſame eternal truth, through the power of God, by which I am made able and carryed on to declare it openly and publickly to the confounding of the heathen, and the reviving of the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for God in the Conſcience, and alſo to ſuffer for the ſame, which I did believe, the Prieſts did much blaſpheme and reproach, ſtriving to preſent it odious to the people, ſo in obedience to the Lord I went out from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt my friends, not telling one of them whither I was agoing (as many can witneſs, and one friend followed me to the dore, and perceiving ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:168328:9"/>of my going, he asked me if he might go with me, and I bid him uſe his freedome to come after, but I deſired to go alone, and ſo I went on the way ſingle, and when I came at the Steeplehouſe dore, which you perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors calls a Church, and alſo accounts your ſelves another Church, and thus you ſet up Churches in your imaginations, yet are ſtrangers to the true Church, which are no perſecutors; but when I came there, there was ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral boys and Children that would have flocked in after me, &amp; I bid them go in before me, rather than to go in diſorderly, whereby to occaſion any diſturbance, and ſo I went in very orderly, and ſtood very orderly, not ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king one word until their peieſt had done, and was coming out of his ſeat, as many can witneſs, though the prieſt had been openly reviling &amp; reproaching the people of God in particular, whom he ſcornfully called quakers, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let all people whoſe underſtandings are enlightned, judge in what rio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous manner I entred the place, which you call a church, &amp; bear witneſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you who are not aſhamed to make lyes your refuge againſt the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent; and alſo what are the weopons which you make uſe of, who calls your ſelves Chriſtians, but makes lyes your refuge, and covers your actions with deceit? But was this the practiſe &amp; nature of Chriſt? for a chriſtian is Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, and let all that profeſs Chriſt, walk as he walked; but theſe are the Fruits of your peblick Humiliation, who go about to mock God, but your end ſhall be according to your works.</p>
                              </div>
                           </div>
                           <div n="2" type="accusation">
                              <head>2 Accuſation.</head>
                              <p>ANd whereas you ſay, being in order thereunto, then exerciſed in the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine worſhip of God Almighty; he (the ſaid <hi>James</hi>) did then, and there ſtand up and told the miniſter he blaſphemed, and ſpoke falſly, and uſed many other reproachful words againſt the ſaid minister.</p>
                              <div type="reply">
                                 <head>Reply.</head>
                                 <p>UNtil him (called Miniſter) had done the Divination of his own Brain, from whence you derive your <hi>Divine VVorſhip,</hi> and was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of his Seat, I did not ſpeak one word unto him, as hundreds can witneſs, and the firſt words that I ſpoke was not as you accuſe me, but this I ſaid,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.29, 30, 31.</note> 
                                    <hi>this is the order of the true Church, that all may ſpeak one by one, and if any thing be revealed to him that ſtands by, let the firſt hold his peace;</hi> then I ſpoke on in the behalf of thoſe people called quakers, whom the <hi>Prieſt</hi> had before often and openly reviled, but ſo ſoon as I had ſpoke a few words, the Prieſt and ſeverall others diſorderly ran into many words, and ſo inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted me in ſpeaking, that it bred much confuſion; then the Prieſt asked me what I would object againſt him, I told him in that he reviled the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple called quakers, and ſaid they was built upon a ſandy foundation, and ſo called them Shakers and the like, but I told him I would prove their
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:168328:9"/>Foundation not to be ſandy, and him to be the falſe Prophet, and ſo I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared of <hi>The Stone cut out of the Mountain without hands, which ſtrikes at the Feet of the Image, whoſe head is Gold, and Breſt of Silver, and Thighes of Braſs and Legs of Iron, and Feet part Iron and part Clay,</hi> and this Stone is become a great Mountain, upon which the Church is built, as a City ſet on a hill cannot be hid; and this is the Foundation of the people that are called quakers, not all that are called quakers, but the real people whom the world ſcornfully calls quakers; and this is become a ſtumbling ſtone, and a rock of offence to the nations, and ſo it ſeems it is unto you, becauſe you are the worſhippers of the great Image, which you call the Divine wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of your God, but God almighty you know not, for he abhors all the ſacrifices of <hi>Cain,</hi> and his Generation, which was ever the perſecuting ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, upon which muſt come all the righteous bloodſhed, from righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Abell</hi> untill now; <hi>therefore wo unto you ye Serpents, ye generation of vipers, how can ye eſcape the damnation of hell?</hi>
                                    <note place="margin">
                                       <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.35. ver. 3 3. <hi>Act.</hi> 5.7 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                          <desc>•</desc>
                                       </gap>.</note> 
                                    <hi>And now you fill up the meaſure of your Fathers wrath; ye ſtiff-necked, and uncircumciſed in hearts and ears, ye do al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies reſiſt the Holy Ghoſt, as did your fathers ſo do ye;</hi> but think not that you ſhall be heard for your much babbling, who for a pretence make long pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, but ye ſhall receive the greater damnation, and the Lord will make your diviners mad, <hi>who hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                          <desc>•</desc>
                                       </gap> ſpoke a Divination from their own brain, and not from the mouth of the Lord, but cryed peace, peace, where there is no peace,</hi>
                                    <note place="margin">
                                       <hi>Iſa.</hi> 44.25 <hi>Ier.</hi> 14.14.</note> 
                                    <hi>becauſe ye put into their mouthes, and ſo heals you ſlightly, daubing you up with untempred morter, but you ſhall all fall amongſt them, that fall in the day that</hi> I <hi>viſit you,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>ye murderers and crucifiers of the juſt:</hi> So when I had clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the foundation of the people called quakers, as aforeſaid, ſome of you accuſed me that I owned no CHURCH, and I ſaid it was falſe; then ſome of you asked me what CHURCH I owned, and I anſwered, the CHURCH in GOD, and more words I ſpoke about the Church; then <hi>VVillis</hi> the DIVINER ſtood up in his Will, and ſaid I ſpoke nothing but non-ſence, and I bid him name one word that was non-ſence that I had ſpoken, and he ſaid, to ſay the Church in GOD, then I took out my BIBLE, and read unto him the firſt Chapter of the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> and the firſt verſe, where the Apoſtle writeth to the Church of the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> which is God the Father; then paleneſs ſtruck the face of the Diviner, neither would any of his fellows ſtand up to juſtifie what he had taken in hand; and this was it wherein I ſaid he blaſphemed, to ſay the Church in God was non-ſence; then there was one Prieſt <hi>Stellum,</hi> a Magician of Aegypt, who ſtood up in the enmity of his ſpirit, and accuſed me with ſeverallys, &amp; ſlanders which hardned <hi>Pharoahs</hi> heart, ſo that you corrupt rulers would not ſuffer me to clear my ſelf from what he had accuſed me withall, but the Magician got up into the ſeat of Divination, and was going to his abomination, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>d then the RULERS called to me to put off my hat, then I bid you call to the Prieſt to put of his cap.</p>
                                 <p>
                                    <pb n="16" facs="tcp:168328:10"/>And thus may all ſee the blindneſs and ignorance of Prieſts and People, who are offended at a hat, and not at a can; and this is as the vain tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of the <hi>Phariſes,</hi> who obſerved the waſhing of Pots and cups, and ſuch like things, making clean the out-ſide, which Scripture Prieſt <hi>VVil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis,</hi> (who ſaid, the <hi>Church in God</hi> was non-ſenſe) brought in reference to the people called Quakers, becauſe they do not put off their hats in reſpect [or worſhipping] of mens perſons; but let any who hath un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, conſider which is more Traditional, for a man to keep his hat on his head, for which end it is made, as alſo his ſhooe for his foot, his glove for his hand, or the putting off theſe things, in obſervation of <hi>cuſtomes,</hi>
                                    <note place="margin">
                                       <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.7, 8, 9.</note> and <hi>reverencing mens perſon,</hi> for all which there is no <hi>Scripture;</hi> therefore a vain <hi>Tradition</hi> of <hi>Man;</hi> and thus they teach for Doctrine the <hi>Traditions of Man;</hi> therefore in <hi>vains do you worſhip God; who come neer him with your lips, and with your mouths, but your hearts are farre from him,</hi>
                                    <note place="margin">
                                       <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.44.</note> 
                                    <hi>in the unbeliefe,</hi> ſeeking honor one of another, and obſerving <hi>vaine Traditions and cuſtomes,</hi> as did your <hi>forefathers,</hi> whom Chriſt pronounced woe againſt, who were his <hi>Perſecutors, and in whoſe ſteps yee are found;</hi> and therefore read your portion: And thus while you are crying againſt the <hi>Scribes and Phariſees</hi> for obſerving <hi>vaine Traditions and cuſtomes,</hi> and their ſtrictneſs in their obſervations, and yet <hi>Perſecutors of the Iuſt;</hi> you alſo are found the ſame, who are ſet up in the chiefeſt <hi>place of the Aſſembly,</hi>
                                    <note place="margin">
                                       <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.</note> as they were, and <hi>called of men Maſter,</hi> as they were, <hi>ſtand praying in the Synagogues,</hi> as they did, <hi>teaching for Doctrine the Traditions of men;</hi> as they did, and are ſtrict in your <hi>Obſervations, and calling of Aſſemblies, and in your ſet-times of VVorſhip, and appointed Paſts and days of Humiliation, and yet are perſecutors of the juſt,</hi> as they were, yea in the very height of your <hi>VVorſhip</hi> the bitterneſs of your <hi>ſpirits</hi> appeared; but is this ſuch a Faſt as God hath choſen? Nay, it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bomination, his Soul loaths it, and hee will judge the cauſe of the <hi>Innocent</hi> upon you <hi>Hypocrites,</hi> and be avenged of you his <hi>Adverſaries,</hi> and give you your portion with <hi>Vnbelievers</hi> in the Lake that burneth, prepared of old for <hi>Cains Generation,</hi> in which you are found, by the <hi>Eternall Light of God,</hi> which cannot lye, which will riſe up in <hi>Iudgement</hi> againſt you at the laſt day, though now you ſtumble at it, and are offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded at it; yet then <hi>ſhal you behold him whom you have pierced,</hi> though with Lamentation and Sorrow of Minde, when there is none to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver you from the wrath of the <hi>Almighty,</hi> and this is anſwered and witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in your Conſciences.</p>
                                 <p>Then the occaſion of my paſſing out of the <hi>Steeple-houſe</hi> was this, when I could not have liberty to ſpeak in the vindication of the Truth, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt gain-ſayers, ye would have had me have ſtood with my hat off the time the Prieſt was praying, which Worſhip I denied, and therefore could not be conformable to it; and ſo I ſaid, before I would ſtay to fulfill your wills, I would paſs out of the <hi>Steeple-houſe,</hi> and many came out after me,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:168328:10"/>but not of my calling, and many that I knew not, and yet you are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed to fay my followers.</p>
                                 <p>And again, That I went into the Common High-way, and there kept with the people unlawfully together, as you affirm, is a very abominable Lye, eſpecially for men of your profeſſion to tell, which many can witneſs againſt, for I was paſſing on the way quietly without diſturbance towards my friends houſe from whence I came, not purpoſing to ſtop until I came there; but that he that writes himſelf <hi>Dyoniſius VVakering</hi> came hurrying in amongſt the people, and clapped me on the back, and ſail, <hi>He arreſted me in the Name of the Protector,</hi> and there ſtopped me, and the firſt words that I ſpoke was, <hi>VVhere is thy VVrit?</hi> and ſo the people gathered about, and thronged much, but that any gave out menacing and threatning ſpeeches J cannot ſay, neither whom they was ſpoken againſt, but any that owns me it is wel-known, they are not men of ſuch boyſtrous ſpirits, but rather are made willing to to be reviled, then to revile, for from me no other example they have, as hundreds will acknowledge; but <hi>VVake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> if the was true to that of God in his conſcience, he would confeſs how I laboured in his preſence to ſtill the people, when he had violently laid hands on me, and given the occaſion; and ſo let all take notice, that there was no diſorder nor diſturbance until the Magiſtrate came and laid violent hands on me, tending to the breach of the peace, and againſt the Law, and this is the fruits of your hypocritical faſt and voluntary humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation.</p>
                              </div>
                           </div>
                           <div n="3" type="accusation">
                              <head>3 <hi>Accuſation.</hi>
                              </head>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>And alſo you accuſe me,</hi> That I could give no good account of my laſt ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or of my life and converſation.</p>
                              <div type="reply">
                                 <head>Reply.</head>
                                 <p>As for my life and converſation, let it preach forth it ſelf, and them that can accuſe me let them; and as for my ſettlement it is in the Lord, where I have found a habitation, and ſo am no vagabond nor wanderer, though I challenge no propriety in the earth, becauſe my Kingdome is not of this world, though you accuſe me that I appear unto you to be an i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle diſorderly perſon, and before you ſet me down <hi>Iames Parnel</hi> Labourer; and thus you utter forth your folly with your changeable minds, but I am a Labourer in the Goſpel of God, in which work none can tax me with i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleneſs, ſince I came into theſe parts, but if I had been more idle in the ſame ye would have been more pleaſed, for it is my great Labor and Diligence in this work of the free Goſpel, and the proſperity thereof, in the overtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and lay open the deceits of deceiving, and deceived men, that tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments you, who are the ſhelterers of the falſe Prophet, whom you carry in your boſome, becauſe he cries peace unto you, when the Lord cries woe; yet nevertheleſs it is but for a time, for the hand of the Almighty is againſt you, and who ſhal deliver you?</p>
                                 <p>And when you have laid all theſe lyes, ſlanders, and falſe accuſations
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:168328:11"/>upon my back, you commit me to the Common Goale for this County, as you ſay, in the name of his Highneſs the Lord Protector, and ſo you make his name a cover for your lies, and a Protector of <hi>perſecution and oppreſſion;</hi> but according to his own Declaration, he took not upon him that place and Title, for that end, but by your proceedings in his Name it doth ſo appear, or elſe the <hi>meſſengers and ſervants of Ieſus Chriſt</hi> would not be ſo perſecuted, and caſt into priſons, and dungeons, and holes, in his Name, as they are; but what a Liberty of Conſcience is this? and how wil this ſtand in the preſence of the Almighty God, who will judge him that judgeth, as wel as him that is judged?</p>
                                 <p>That all Sects, Forms, Judgements, and Opinions ſhould be at liberty, and be protected therein, and the dear children of God perſecuted and impriſoned, and ſhamefully intreated as they are, and all this done in the Name of the <hi>Lord Protector of England;</hi> therefore in the day of the Lords vengeance, he wil be avenged of all his <hi>Adverſaries</hi> from the leaſt to the greateſt, and who ſhal eſcape his hand in the day that hee will deliver his own, and advance them above all their enemies, though here you his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies have caſt me, you ſay, <hi>until I ſhal be delivered by due courſe of Law.</hi>
                                 </p>
                                 <p>
                                    <hi>Reply.</hi> What law or juſtice can I expect from ſuch unjuſt Lawyers and Judges as you are? for you that caſt me in contrary and without Law, it is likely you wil proceed contrary and without Law, for your owne Law wil bear witneſs and teſtifie againſt you to your ſhame and confuſion of face, though to this Libel you have ſet your hands and ſeals, who write yourſelves, <hi>Herbert Pellham, Thomas Cook, Dyoniſius VVakering, VVilliam Harlackinden.</hi>
                                 </p>
                                 <p>
                                    <hi>Here let your hands bear witneſs, and teſtifie againſt you, for enemies and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors of the juſt, who bind heavy burthens, and lay them upon the oppreſſed, but wil not touch them with one of your fingers, but the greater will be your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation when there is none to deliver you from the hand of the</hi> Almighty, <hi>nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Rocks nor Mountains to ſhelter you, but the refuge of lies ſhal be done away, therefore while you have time prize it, and bring your deeds to the light, and owne your condemnation by the light, that your ſouls may be ſaved; now you are warned and the meſsenger of the Lord diſcharged, by whom you are warned, and the truth cleared from your lyes and falſe accuſations, which in the enmity of your ſpirits you have caſt upon it; and ſo in the liberty and peace I reſt and ſtand, wherein</hi> Chriſt <hi>hath ſet me free, which none cat take away, who am a ſufferer in outward bonds for the teſtimony of a</hi> pure conſcience, <hi>at</hi> Colcheſter-Caſtle, <hi>who am known to you my</hi> perſecutors <hi>by the name,</hi>
                                 </p>
                              </div>
                           </div>
                        </div>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>J. Parnel.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <q>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:168328:11"/>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="queries">
                        <head>Here followeth a copy of ſome <hi>Quaeres</hi> that was ſent with the foregoing Letter, to the Iuſtices ſo called.</head>
                        <p>Several Quaeres to all you Magiſtrates and Officers, and proud and lofty ones, who rage, perſecute and deſpiſe men, becauſe they cannot put off their hats to you; and call it a contemning of Authority, and miſ-beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, and yet ſay, you are Chriſtian Magiſtrates, and profeſs the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to be your rule; now try your ſelves and prove your practiſe by the Scripture, and by it anſwer theſe quaeries.</p>
                        <p n="1">1 <hi>Quaere.</hi> WHat Rule have you in the Scripture for the putting off the hat?</p>
                        <p n="2">2 What is that in man that would be honoured with the putting off the hat, or bowing the knee?</p>
                        <p n="3">3. Why is it called curteſie to put off the hat to the poor, and honor, &amp; manners, and due reſpect, to put off the hat to the rich?</p>
                        <p n="4">4. Whether is this reſpect of perſons, becauſe of advantage, yea or nay; or what makes this difference.</p>
                        <p n="5">5. Where is your example for this amongſt all the Chriſtians under the Goſpel, as you profeſs.</p>
                        <p n="6">6. And what is that in man that ſo ſwells, and cauſeth ſuch wrath and rage to appear againſt another, for not putting off the hat, if the putting of the hat or bowing the knee be ſuch a ſmal matter as ſome accounts it.</p>
                        <p n="7">7. Whether is that right Authority or Juſtice in man, that commands his fellow-creature to put off the hat before him, and ſo to ſtand untill he ſuffer him to put it on; and if he do not ſo ſtand, then to fall into wrath and rage, and ſay he contemns Authority, yea or nay.</p>
                        <p n="8">8. Where is there any Law that commands a man to put off his hat to one man more than another.</p>
                        <p n="9">9. And if there was a Law that did ſo command,<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Iames</hi> 2.9.</note> whether he that obeys the Law of God that commands no reſpect of perſons, and diſobeys the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Law, do contemn Authority, yea or nay.</p>
                        <p n="10">10. Whether was that Authority in <hi>Hamon</hi> to be obeyed,<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Eaſt.</hi> 3.</note> (who was a chiefe Ruler) and would have had <hi>Mordecai</hi> to have bowed unto him.</p>
                        <p n="11">11. And what was that in <hi>Hamon</hi> that made him full of wrath, ſo that he would ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e deſtroyed <hi>Mordecai,</hi> and all the Jews in the Nation, becauſe <hi>Mordecai</hi> could not bow unto him; and what difference is there betwixt <hi>Hamon</hi> and you in this matter, who now are ful of wrath and rage, and impriſon thoſe that cannot put off their hats to you.</p>
                        <p n="12">12. And whether was that miſ-behaviour, or a contemning of Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in <hi>Mordecai,</hi> in not obeying the Kings command to bow unto <hi>Hamon,</hi> as you ſay it is in not putting off the hat, or bowing to you now; and wherein do you ſee any difference betwixt theſe men now, and <hi>Mordecai</hi> in that matter, ſeeing they ſuffer impriſonment before they can do it.</p>
                        <p n="13">
                           <pb n="20" facs="tcp:168328:12"/>13. And what Lordſhip and authority was that, which they that were accounted to rule over the Gentiles,<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Mat.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>.25.</note> did exerciſe upon them which Chriſt declared againſt to his Diſciples, and wherein do you differ from them in what matter?</p>
                        <p n="14">14. And what honour was that which the Phariſees received one of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother,<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Ioh.</hi> 54.4.</note> for which cauſe Chriſt judged them to be in the unbelief, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you be not guilty of the ſame, yea or nay?</p>
                        <p n="15">15. And what is the honour which commeth from God, which Chriſt there ſpoke of; and whether it ſtands in the putting off a hat, ye a or nay?</p>
                        <p n="16">16. What is the Beaſt which all the world worſhips and wonders after? and what is the worſhip of that Beaſt and his image?<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.3.8.</note> and whether the power and authority of that beaſt is to be obeyed, yea or nay?</p>
                        <p n="17">17. How is Juſtice to be honoured?</p>
                        <p n="18">18. And whether a man may not put off his hat to a Magiſtrate, and yet envie him and hate him in his heart? And whether many in theſe dayes do not ſo? and whether this be the honour that a Magiſtrate ought to ſeek for, yea or nay?</p>
                        <p n="19">19. And whether a man may not honor Juſtice and Equity in his heart without putting off a hat to a Magiſtrate? and he that ſo doth, Whether is he fit to be called a Magiſtrate, that calleth ſuch a one a contemner of au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and commits him to Priſon for mis-behaviour; and whether this be Juſtice or Equity, yea or nay?</p>
                        <p n="20">20. And you that pleads this Scripture, <hi>Be ſubject to every Ordinance of man for the Lords ſake;</hi> whether is it for the Lords ſake that a man would have his Fellow-Creature to ſtand with his hat off before him or for his ſelfes ſake, and whether then it is to be obeyed, yea or nay?</p>
                        <p n="21">21. And he that for the Lords ſake and for conſcience ſake cannot ſo rob God of his Glory and honour, as to bow to, or Worſhip any creature but God alone who is the Creator: Whether ought he to be impriſoned for misbehaviour, or a contemner of authority, yea or nay, according to the law of equity, and whether this is to be called liberty of conſcience, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Law of England, yea or nay?</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Now all you that profeſs your ſelves chriſtians, and the Scripture to be your Rule, take the Scripture and prove your practiſe by the Scripture amongſt all the christians, or elſe let the life and practiſe of the true chriſtians judge you and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem you, and own your ſelves to be in proud</hi> Hamons <hi>nature, and ſo liable to</hi> Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons <hi>judgement; and henceforward look to your Office, to rule for God and not for your ſelves, and then you will not ſtand upon ſuch frivolous things, for it is a frivolous thing to look for the putting off the hat, and is no part of true nobility or chriſtianity.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>Given forth for the clearing of the truth, to which the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons muſt bow,</dateline>
                           <signed>I. P.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <q>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:168328:12"/>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="note">
                        <head>Here followeth a Copy of a Note that was written againſt the <hi>Idolls-Temple,</hi> which was iudged a contempt of the Ministry.</head>
                        <p>THis is the Idols-Temple, where the worſhip of the Beaſt is upheld, down with it, down with it, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.10. <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.7, 8. <hi>Dut.</hi> 12. <hi>God that made the world and all things therein, dwels not in Temples made with hands, Act.</hi> 7.47, 48, 49. <hi>Act.</hi> 17.21. neither is he worſhipped in Idolls-Temples made with mens hands, <hi>Act.</hi> 17.24. <hi>God is a ſpirit, and they that worſhip him muſt worſhip him in ſpirit and in truth;</hi> for the Father is ſeeking ſuch to worſhip him, <hi>Iohn</hi> 23.24. <hi>All the world wonders after and worſhips the beaſt, but thoſe who have their name; written in the book of life, Rev.</hi> 13.3.4.8. <hi>And they that worſhips the Beaſt receives his mark in their foreheads, Rev.</hi> 13.16. <hi>as ſprincking Infants, and worſhipping the works of their own hands,</hi> Iſa. 2.8. <hi>And following the imagination of their own hearts, ſuch muſt drink of the wine of the wrath of the Almighty; powred out without mixture,</hi> Rev. 14.9, 10, 11.12.</p>
                        <p>This Idoll-Temple that is made with hands, is <hi>a place for N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ght-birds, and Skrich Owles to meet each one with his male,</hi> Jer. 34.13, 14, 15. <hi>to the diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the only true God, that dwelleth in temples made without hands, at new Ieruſalem, where the tabernacle of God is with men, Rev.</hi> 21.3. Drunkards and Swearers, Revilers, and Scoffers, and Scorners, proud and wanton ones, Hypocrites and Diſſemblers, envious Haters, Backbiters, Perſecutors, Iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full covetous ones, and Earth-worms meets here, the fearful and unbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, peeviſh, perverſe, contentious ones meets in theſe Idols-Temples, to ſatisfie their luſts; and ſaith the Lord, <hi>theſe people draw neer me with their mouths, and honour me with their lips, but their hearts are far from me; but in vain do they worſhip me, teaching for Doctrine the traditions of men, Mat.</hi> 15.7, 8, 9. <hi>But know you not that no unrighteous perſon ſhall inherit the Kingdome of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 6.9, 10. <hi>But must be cut down and caſt into the Lake that burneth,</hi> Rev. 21.8. <hi>Be not deceived, God is not mocked, ſuch as you ſow, ſuch muſt you reap,</hi> Gal. 6.7. <hi>And to whom you yeild your members ſervants to obey, his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants you are,</hi> Rom. 6.16. <hi>For he that commits ſin is the ſervant of ſin, and ſo is of the Devill. Ioh.</hi> 6.34. 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.</p>
                        <p>This is a Deceiver that ſtands up here every firſt day of the week to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the people, he is proud and Covetous, and ſpeaketh a divination of his own brain, but not from the mouth of the Lord, and ſo makes the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple light and vain, <hi>Ier.</hi> 14.14. But the Lord is againſt him, hold him not up, for he ran and the Lord never ſent him therefore he profits not the people at all, <hi>Ier.</hi> 23.21, 22.32. but hath ſtoln the Letter, which is car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:168328:13"/>with it to feed the carnall, for carnall ends and lucre, and ſo hath a form but denyes the li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e and power, and therefore from him turn away, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5. <hi>therefore ſpend not your moneys for that which is not bread, nor your labour for that which profiteth not,</hi> Iſa. 55.1, 2 <hi>for all the children of the Lord are and ſhall be taught of the Lord, and in righteouſneſs ſhall they be eſtabliſhed, and they ſhall be far from oppreſſion,</hi> Ier. 31.34. Iſa. 54 13, 14. 1 John 2.27</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>He that hath an car to hear let him hear what the ſpirit ſaith, and be deceived no longer.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>J. P.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="queries">
                        <head>Here followeth ſeverall queries that was ſent to four of the chiefe Prieſts in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> with ſome more added, which may be ſerviceable for them, or any other, to anſwer, whom they do concern.</head>
                        <p>SEverall queries unto Prieſt <hi>Sammes,</hi> Prieſt <hi>Sparrow,</hi> Prieſt <hi>VVillis,</hi> and Prieſt <hi>Stellum,</hi> and your gathered Churches, by you to be anſwered ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Scripture, which you profeſs to be your rule.</p>
                        <p>Query 1. How and by what was you called to the Miniſtry which you profe's.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. What is the Goſpel which you pretend to preach, and how did you receive it, and whether your Goſpel be free and without charge; as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles was, yea or nay?</p>
                        <p n="3">3. What do you Miniſter from, and what do you Miniſter to, in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall man, and what is the end of your Miniſtry?</p>
                        <p n="4">4. What rule have you in the Scripture, to take a Text of the Apoſtles words, and ſpeak from it what you have ſtudyed, with your Uſes, Points, Tryalls and Motives, and Applications?</p>
                        <p n="5">5. Whether do you ſpeak by the ſame infallible ſpirit as they did that ſpoke forth the Scripture, yea or nay?</p>
                        <p n="6">6. And whether he that hath the ſame infallible ſpirit, need ſtudy how or what to preach?</p>
                        <p n="7">7. And whether it is not as lawful now for Fiſher-men, Plow-men, or Herds-men, to preach, if they be called to it, and fitted for it, by the ſame power and ſpirit as they was in the dayes of old, and whether Chriſt is not the ſame yeſterday, to day and for ever according to Scripture?</p>
                        <p n="8">8. And whether any now ought to teach and preach in the name of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, but who are caled to it and fitted for it, the ſame way as the holy men of God was, ſpoken of in Scripture?</p>
                        <p n="9">9. Whether do you own immediate Revelation now, yea or nay?</p>
                        <p n="10">
                           <pb n="23" facs="tcp:168328:13"/>10. What is a Miniſter of Chriſt, and what is a Miniſter of Antichriſt, and do you diſtinguiſh the one from the other?</p>
                        <p n="11">11. What Scripture haſt thou to give unto the <hi>world Davids conditions</hi> to be ſung in a Meeter.</p>
                        <p n="12">12. What rule have you in the Scripture, <hi>to abide in a certain place, and to agree with the people for ſo much a year for preaching, as</hi> 40, 60, <hi>or</hi> 100. <hi>or</hi> 200. <hi>l. as you can get it.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="13">13. How and by what are you gathered and united, <hi>who calls your ſolves a Church.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="14">14. And what is the Church in God, and whether to it you be come, yea or nay?</p>
                        <p n="15">15. What is the Baptiſme into the Church, and whether to it you be come, yea or nay?</p>
                        <p n="16">16 And Scripture have you to ſprinckle children with water, <hi>and to what end do you do it?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="17">17. Whether you be of one heart and one mind, as the true Church was yea or nay?</p>
                        <p n="18">18. Whether you have paſſed from death to life, yea or nay.</p>
                        <p n="19">19. What is the faith of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; <hi>and whether to it you be come, yea or nay?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="20">20. Whether <hi>he that believes is not born of God;</hi> and whether he <hi>that is born of God,</hi> doth not <hi>commit ſin,</hi> yea or nay?</p>
                        <p n="21">21. Why do not you maintain your Teacher, <hi>but let him rob the world in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of robbing other Churches, and ſo is chargeable unto the world?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="22">22. Whether do you own and hold up the firſt <hi>Prieſt-hood,</hi> that took Tythes, or the ſecond <hi>Prieſt-hood</hi> that took no Tythes, and which do you deny, ſeeing you pay tythes, and your Teacher takes tythes, yea or nay?</p>
                        <p n="23">23. Why do you own and hold up ſuch that <hi>are called of men Maſter, and have the chiefeſt place in the Aſſemblie, and ſtand praying in the Synagogue, and love greetings in the Markets,</hi> which Chriſt himſelf cryed wo againſt.</p>
                        <p n="24">24. How is <hi>Chriſt the light of the world,</hi> and how doth he <hi>enlighten every one that cometh into the world,</hi> if it be not in the <hi>conſcience;</hi> and whether that Light which comes from him be naturall, yea or nay?</p>
                        <p n="25">25. How is the light <hi>the condemnation of the world,</hi> if it be not in the <hi>conſcience</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="26">26. And how is it ſaid, <hi>that he that doth evill hateth the light, and wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>l not bring his deeds to the Light,</hi> leſt <hi>the Light ſhould reprove him,</hi> if it be not in the <hi>conſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience,</hi> &amp; whether that be a natural light which reproves for ſin, yea or nay.</p>
                        <p n="27">27. How did <hi>Paul</hi> turn <hi>peoples mindes from darkneſs to light,</hi> if it be not in the <hi>conſcience,</hi> and whether that light was naturall which <hi>Paul</hi> was ſent to turn the mindes of the Gentiles unto.</p>
                        <p n="28">28. Whether that light which ſhines in darkneſs, be not one, and the ſame, with that which ſhines out of darkneſs, yea or nay?</p>
                        <p n="29">29. And whether the light of the world be not a ſaving light in the leaſt meaſure, yea or nay? and how can that be ſaid to be naturall?</p>
                        <p n="30">
                           <pb n="24" facs="tcp:168328:14"/>30. Whether the Light which <hi>Iohn</hi> came to beare witneſs of, was natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall or ſpirituall?</p>
                        <p n="31">31. How hath the grace of God, which bringeth Salvation, appeared to all men, if it be not in the conſcience, and whether it be naturall.</p>
                        <p n="32">32. How doth it ſtand with the impartiall God, to give to one man a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of grace, and not to another, and yet require obedience from all.</p>
                        <p n="33">33. Whether the ſlothfull ſervant hath not a Talent as wel as the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, though he hide it in the earth, and what is that Talent.</p>
                        <p n="34">34. What is the account that God wil require of every one in the day of Judgment, and how can he call all juſtly to an account, and reward them according to their deeds, if he hath not given to every one a Talent.</p>
                        <p n="35">35. What is that which leads to repentance; and whether that which leads to repentance be not in the conſcience, and whether it be naturall yea or nay.</p>
                        <p n="36">36. And where do you read in the Scripture of a naturall light to be in the conſcience.</p>
                        <p n="37">37. What is the redemption; and what is the end of Chriſts coming.</p>
                        <p n="38">38. Whether the redemption by Chriſt, be not as ful in every in every reſpect, as the fall by <hi>Adam,</hi> and what is the fall by <hi>Adam.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="39">39. And whether you do not go about to make the commands of Chriſt unjuſt, who ſaith, <hi>Be ye perfect, as your heavenly father is perfect;</hi> and you ſay it cannot be while you are upon the earth, then how is it your rule.</p>
                        <p n="40">40. Will you own a purgatory, or where is the place betwixt heaven and earth where man ſhall be clenſed, if not upon the earth, ſeeing no unclean thing can inherit the kingdome of God.</p>
                        <p n="41">41 Whether do they deny Chriſt come in the fleſh, that witneſs forth perfection from ſin here, or they that tel people they can never be perfect, or be wholly ſet free from ſin ſo long as they are upon the earth, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch be not the Miniſters of Antichriſt, yea or nay.</p>
                        <p n="42">42. Where had you this Doctrine to tell people the light in the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is naturall, and that Chriſt hath not enlightned every one that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth into the world.</p>
                        <p n="43">43. And whether in this you do not bring another Doctrine, in oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Doctrine of Chriſt, who ſaith he is the light of the world, and doth enlighten every one that cometh into the world.</p>
                        <p n="44">44. And where had you this Doctrine, to tel people they could never be wholly clenſed, or be ſet free from ſin, ſo long as they are upon the Earth.</p>
                        <p n="45">45. And whether this be not in oppoſition to the Doctrine of Chriſt, who ſaith, <hi>Be ye perfect, as your heavenly Father is perfect.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="46">46. Whether God <hi>juſtifies</hi> any in their ſin; and whether ſanctification go not before juſtification, yea or nay.</p>
                        <p n="47">47. Whether you do not ſeek juſtification by works, who put one another upon prayer, and duties, obſervations, Ordinances, and commands, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:168328:14"/>the Light, in imitation of the Letter, and whether theſe be not your own works which are done out of the light, yea or nay.</p>
                        <p n="48">48. What is your own righteouſneſs, and what is the righteouſneſs of Chriſt, and how do you diſtinguiſh betwixt the one and the other?</p>
                        <p n="49">49. And whether he that is juſtified by the righteouſneſs of Chriſt, doth not dwel in it, and it in him, and whether he that dwels in the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Chriſt doth ſin, yea or nay.</p>
                        <p n="50">50 Whether any can walk according to the Scripture but by the Light of Chriſt; and whether any that are guided by the Light of Chriſt, do, or can act contrary to the Scripture; and whether this Light be not a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent guide, if it be owned and followed?</p>
                        <p n="51">51. How is the Scripture left unto the world for a rule, who know not the Light, ſeeing to them it is a parable, and as a book ſealed.</p>
                        <p n="52">52. And what is the word, and whether there be any other word of God then one?</p>
                        <p n="53">53. What is the death that hath paſſed over all men, forasmuch as all men have ſinned; and whether this death you ever paſſed, yea or nay.</p>
                        <p n="54">54. What is that which is loſt, which Chriſt comes to ſeek; and what is that which was driven away, which Chriſt comes to bring again; and whether this is not to be witneſſed and fulfilled in man, yea or nay.</p>
                        <p n="55">55. What is the Paradiſe wherein man was placed; and what was the Image of God wherein man was created.</p>
                        <p n="56">56. And how was man a living ſoul; and whether all this is not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored unto man, and fulfilled and witneſſed unto man, while he is upon the earth, yea or nay.</p>
                        <p n="57">57. What is the Tree of Life, and what is the Tree of Knowledge, and whether upon it you do not feed; and what is the flaming ſword that is ſet to keep from the tree of life, and whether it you ever paſſed.</p>
                        <p n="58">58. Whether the naturall man can try and diſcern falſe ſpirits by the Scripture; and by what doth the ſpirituall man try and judge all things, and whether by the ſame he did not try and diſcern ſpirits.</p>
                        <p n="59">59. And by what did the holy men of God that gave forth the Scripture try and diſcern ſpirits; and whether yours be the ſame tryer of ſpirits as theirs was, who ſay you muſt try the ſpirit by the Letter.</p>
                        <p n="60">60. Whether you are not conformed like unto the world, ſo long as you follow their faſhions and cuſtomes.</p>
                        <p n="61">61. Whether you are not partiall amongſt your ſelves, ſo long as you reſpect perſons.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Theſe things</hi> I <hi>do not ask as if</hi> I <hi>knew them not, but for the ſatisfaction of the ſimple, and the clearing of the truth, and manifeſting your deceit to the world, by which you have deceived the world, who are the deceivers of the world, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore anſwer by plain Scripture, and your own experience, or elſe let all fleſh keep ſilence before the Lord, and let guilt ſtop your mouths, for Rayling, reproaching,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:168328:15"/>and blaſpheming the truth of God, which is made manifeſt in theſe people, whom you ſcornfully calls quakers, who by you and your agents are perſecuted, but where do you find that the Church of God was ever perſecutors, or ever made uſe of carnall weapons to defend them.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>J. P.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>Here followeth a Copy of a Letter that I was moved to write to Iudge <hi>Hills,</hi> after the Aſſize.</head>
                  <p>A Few words unto thee that art ſet in the ſeat to do juſtice, and to bear the ſword of Juſtice in thy hand, and haſt turned the edg of it againſt the righteous, and laid it upon the innocent, and thy fair words wil not ſhelter nor cover thy deceitful actions, but thy deceitful heart is made manifeſt, and thy hypocriſie doth thee appear, for thou haſt hearkned unto the falſe Prophet,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iſai.</hi> 5.10.</note> and by his enticing words thou art deceived, and ſo puts darkneſs for light, and light for darkneſs, evill for good, and good for evil, and ſo art liable to the wo from the Lord, and haſt perſecuted Chriſt, and ſet at liberty <hi>Barabas,</hi> yea, and I was numbred amongſt tranſgreſſors, yet could not have the liberty of tranſgreſſors, as in many things might be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated, but in ſhort I ſhall declare it; firſt, that mine accuſers ſhould ſtand in the place as judges over me, and their accuſations and falſe witneſſes to be heard to the ful, and alſo to whiſper and buz in thy eares in ſecret, what they would againſt me, and alſo that thou that ſate in the ſeat as a Judge to repeat over unto the Jury all that thou couldſt gather by wrong interpretation, and conſtruction againſt me, but nothing of my defence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt my accuſations, but rather to drive out of their minds, by thy evill incenſing, what I had before declared in my own defence, but thou, as it were, paſsed the ſentence upon me before the Jury went ſorth, but thou thoughteſt thou hadſt pannelled a Jury wherewith thou waſt pleaſed to try me according to thine own mind and will, for the <hi>Foreman</hi> was a drunkard, and the reſt ſwearers, <hi>out of the Doctrine of Chriſt,</hi> againſt all which I did <hi>object,</hi> and denyed by them to be tryed, but it was thy wil and pleaſure ſo to do, and when they come to bring in their evidence, they had ſo much un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, that they charged me with nothing, but the papers which I had before confeſſed to be mine, and owned them, but the Indictment they would not own to be truth againſt me, though diſhoneſtly both thou and the Clerk, did draw <hi>words</hi> out of the <hi>Foreman</hi> of the Jury, which the reſt did not conſent to, and then in thy wil, with thy fair and deceitful ſpeeches thou impoſed a fine upon me, contrary to all law and equity, but where e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity is not it cannot be expected, for <hi>oppreſſion</hi> within, <hi>oppreſſion</hi> without, and he that cannot witneſs the ſword of juſtice ſet up in his heart, knows not how to handle it without, for he that rules not by the law of <hi>God</hi> in his heart rules in his own wil, and is partial &amp; underſtands not the things of God, but what pleaſeth his wil, that he cheriſheth, &amp; what croſseth his will that he would curb, and the wil of man is oppoſite to the wil of God, therefore the Croſs of Chriſt is of uſe to them that know it, but a ſtumbling block to the world; but he that rules in his own wil is no miniſter of God, he that reſpects
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:168328:15"/>perſons is not fit to bear rule for God, he that ſeeks himſelf is not fit to bear rule for God; all which appeared, and was openly manifeſt in thee in the open Court, as in thoſe things beforementioned, and many other which are now out of mind; but for the clearing of my conſcience unto thee, I was moved to write, that thou might'ſt ſee what thou haſt done, and be left without excuſe of ignorance in the preſence of the Almighty; for contrary to the <hi>Light of God in thy conſcience</hi> thou haſt acted, by which thou ſtands accuſed in the <hi>preſence of the Almighty,</hi> and if thy <hi>conſcience</hi> accuſe thee, <hi>God</hi> is greater; but if thou hadſt ſtood in the place where thou art ſet, to judge of <hi>legal malters,</hi> about <hi>natural and temporal things,</hi> thou hadſt had the leſs to account for, but in medling to judge about <hi>ſpiritual matters,</hi> is authority which the <hi>Scripture</hi> (which thou calls thy rule) doth not allow thee; for <hi>the natural man receives not the things of God, becauſe they are ſpiritually diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned;</hi> therefore in this the <hi>ſpiritual man</hi> judgeth thee, and thy <hi>condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is great;</hi> therefore lay theſe things to heart, and put them not far from thee, for to the <hi>light of God in thy conſcience</hi> I do ſpeak, which eternally wil witneſs me and condemn thee in the preſence of the <hi>Almighty,</hi> who haſt taken upon thee to judge and condemn thoſe whom God hath juſtified; therefore conſider what advantageth it thee, or what wil it advancage thee when thou comes to give an account before the Lord God of Heaven and Earth, the <hi>Iudge of all the quick and the dead,</hi> it thou haſt now power to keep this body in priſon until thou haſt the life of the creature, which I am freely made willing to give up, rather then to deny the truth of my God, and if I ſhould pay one penny for the liberty of my body in this cauſe, would be as much as if I paid the whole fine which thou haſt unjuſtly laid upon me; for therein I ſhould own my ſelf a Tranſgreſſor where I am not guilty; and alſo a <hi>bought liberty is bondage to my ſpirit,</hi> but my <hi>liberty under thy bonds</hi> is bondage to thee, which <hi>liberty</hi> thou canſt not rob me of, with all that thou canſt do, for it is <hi>the free gift of God,</hi> which none can take away, though thou wilt not allow me in thy <hi>bonds</hi> to have the <hi>outward liberty</hi> that thou allows to <hi>Thieves,</hi> and <hi>Murderers,</hi> and <hi>Fornicators,</hi> that is, <hi>to have my friends and acquaintance to come to ſeeme,</hi> wherein the very heathen wil con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn thee, who when they had committed <hi>Paul</hi> to priſon, ſaid, <hi>Forbid none of his friends and acquaintance to come to fee him, Acts</hi> 22.24. Therefore now read how thou exceeds the <hi>Heathen</hi> in <hi>perſecution</hi> and <hi>injuſtice,</hi> though I am a <hi>free-born ſubject</hi> in <hi>England;</hi> therefore let the life of all the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn thee who never was <hi>perſecutors.</hi> And <hi>this of the Lord I was moved to write, which is the VVord of the Lord unto thee, whether thou wil hear or forbear, in the peace of my conſcience I do reſt in the VVill of God.</hi> Known to thee by the name,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Iames Parnel.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:168328:16"/>And now a few words unto you who call your ſelves gathered Churches, who go under by the name of Independants in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> you are gathered by the wil of man, and are joyned by the wil of man, and ſo ſtands in the will of man, and are upheld by the wil of man, by which you are begotten, but ſtil alive in the worlds nature, in the worlds cuſtomes, faſhions, and traditions, in the worlds fellowſhip, words and waies, and rudiments, only differing from others in judgement, opinion, or profeſſion, wherein is your life in high notions, and feigned apprehenſions, and falſe applications, and glorious expreſſions, and cuſtomary duties, and vain Traditions, which all appertains to the great Image, which all the world worſhips; by which they are deceived, whoſe head is gold, and breſt of ſilver, and thighs of braſs, and legs of Iron, and feet part Iron and part clay: and in the ſame nature ye are found with the world, the day doth declare it, and you to be the enemies and ſtrangers to the light, which is not of the world, which is now come into the world, teſtifying againſt the world; and the deceit of the world, &amp; the deceivers in the world, and the profeſſion of the world and <hi>this is the condemnation of the world,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 3.19.</note> 
               <hi>that light is come into the world, and men love dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs rather than light, becauſe their deeds are evill;</hi> in which evil you are found, deſpiſing and ſett<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng at nought the Corner-ſtone, and ſtanding in the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of your ſpirits, and joyning with the powers of the earth, to perſecute the life and power which now is manifeſt in the earth, and is come to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover your empty ſhadows, forms, and fair ſhews of godlineſs, but without life and power, which you have ſet up in your imaginations, and thereby are deceived, and blinded, and led in blindneſs, ſo that you cannot ſee the light, nor receive the ſubſtance, now it is come and made manifeſt, but ſtands up in your wills and wiſdome to oppoſe the ſame, and perſecute it in the enmity of your ſpirits, as if you hoped to kill the heir, that the inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance might be yours; and therefore becauſe you do deſpiſe this day of your viſitation, and reject &amp; ſlight the glad tydings which now are come to them that dwel upon the earth, and revile, and reproach, perſecute and ſlander the faithfull meſſengers of the Goſpell, rejoycing your hearts in their ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, by you and amongſt you, therefore the Lord will rayſe up a people out of the duſt, &amp; gather them from far, to bear teſtimony unto his name and bear witneſs againſt you, yea, and ſhall ſit down with <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Iacob,</hi> in the kingdome of the Son, and you, and ſuch as you, ſhall be caſt out into <hi>Tophit,</hi> prepared of old for hypocrites and unbelievers,, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore now read your portions ye ſtiff-necked, and uncircumciſed in hearts &amp; cars, who do alwayes reſiſt the Holy Ghoſt, as did your fathers ſo do ye, but the greater wil be your condemnation, who go about to mock God with your wil-worſhip, with your calling of Aſſemblies, and Solemn Meetings, with your appointed Faſts, and dayes of voluntary Humiliation, with your long Prayers and feigned duties, all which is done out of the Light, and ſo are your own works, acted by ſelfe, for ſelfe But who hath required theſe things at your hands? it is all abomination to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:168328:16"/>the Lord, his ſoul loaths it, for your ſacrifices are as <hi>Cain</hi>'s, for your are found in <hi>Cain</hi>'s nature, envying and perſecuting the righteous, yea the witneſs lies ſlain in your ſtreets, therefore wo is unto you who go on in the way of <hi>Cain,</hi> for upon you ſhal come all the righteous blood ſhed from righteous <hi>Abel</hi> until now; and your profeſſions ſtinks in the noſtrils of the Lord, for you have lift up your hands againſt him and his Annoynted, &amp; opened your mouths in blaſphemy, and falſe reports againſt the truth; yea, you are blinde, and ſtumble at the noon day, you come neer the Lord with your lips, but your hearts runs awhoring after other Lovers, and you know not the only true God, that dwels in Temples made without hands, whoſe worſhip is in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and in truth, but would limit the unlimited under your wils, as if he were not a God of might, but that you could controle him with the arm of fleſh, but be not deceived, God is not mocked, ſuch as you ſowe, ſuch ſhall you reap, and your end ſhal be according to your works;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.7.</note> for our God is a God of Judgement and Juſtice, &amp; wil avenge the cauſe of the innocent upon you his adverſaries, yea and though your Teachers do cry peace, peace un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, becauſe you put into their mouths, and ſo daubs you up with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempred morter, that you cannot ſee your wound, and ſo heals you ſlightly, yet you ſhal know that our God is a God of Truth and his word ſhal ſtand for ever, and their ſorcery ſhal appear, and their witchcraft ſhal be laid o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, and the cup of fornication (wherewith they have made drunk and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded the Nations) ſhal be taken from them, and the cup of the wrath of the Almighty given them to drink their reward, and then ſhal you behold the Harlot with whom you have committed fornication, who now lies in your boſomes, bewitching you with a golden cup, with whom you have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed your garments, then to be caſt into the bottomleſs pit, where you ſhal all be tormented together, who now partake of her pleaſures, and thus ſhal you fal amongſt them that fal in the day that I viſit you, ſaith the Lord.</p>
            <p>And all you my dear friends, you ſcattered and deſpiſed ones in and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the County of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> whom the Lord by his powerful word is now ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering out of darkneſs into his marvellous light, out of the Kingdome of this World, into the Kingdome of his dear Son, whom he is ſeperating un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to himſelf to walk before him in holineſs, that you might know him, and he might know you in the light of his countenance, whoſe faces he hath turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to words <hi>Sion,</hi> to ſeek after a Land of Reſt unto your wearied Souls which hath been toſſed to and fro, from mountain to hil in this cloudy and dark day, ſeeking reſt but finding none; but now is the day of beauty broken forth nigh you, even in you, yea &amp; glad tidings is come unto your wearied ſouls, by which a pure love is begotten in you to the everlaſting truth, which hath been freely declared amongſt you by the meſſengers of the moſt high, who hath reached the witneſs for God in your conſciences, which doth ſeal the ſame upon your hearts, which your teacher is, and unto it you hearken, and are abedient, in which light all ſtand ſtil, &amp; behold the work which the Lord hath begun amongſt you, and you ſhal have no cauſe of diſcouragement, though the ſea do riſe, and the raging waves do ſwel as if they would ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:168328:17"/>all up, yet it is limited by the unlimited, &amp; it ſhal but foam out its own ſhame. And as I had a time to preach the truth amongſt you, to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincement of many, ſo alſo now I have a time to ſeal the ſame with patient ſuffering in the bonds of the Goſpel, that you may ſee that it is no other but what we are made able and willing to ſeal with patient ſuffering, yea with our blood if we be called to it, as many of us hath done in this Nation, though it be called a Land of Liberty, but it is for Iniquity, but truth and equity are ſtrangers in it, &amp; therefore are perſecuted, but you that are found worthy to receive theſe ſtrangers happy are you; &amp; though the raging So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domites compaſs you about for to cauſe you to caſt out theſe ſtrangers, that they may work their wils upon them, yet be faithful and fear them not, but caſt out your darlings before them, &amp; ſtand in the faith of the God of truth, &amp; equity, and you ſhal ſee the <hi>Sodomites</hi> ſtruck with blindneſs, that they ſhal not be able to prevail againſt you, but when they are weary with ſtriving they ſhal be made to ſit down in ſorrow, &amp; ſo ſhal it be fulfill d which of old was propheſied, <hi>that no weapon formed againſt the faithful ſhal proſper, but woe unto them that lift up their heel againſt them;</hi> therefore I charge you all in the name of the God of truth, be faithful, valiant, &amp; bold for the truth received, and as you have received it, ſo walk in it, that you may profeſs no more in word but what in life you ſeal, that the light may be preached forth in your lives, &amp; ſhine forth in your converſations, to the glory of the father of lights and the confounding of the heathen, who profeſs God in words, but in life denies him, &amp; be willing that ſelf ſhal ſuffer for the truth, and not the truth for ſelf; for the truth was ever ſealed with perſecution ſince <hi>Cains</hi> generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on had a being upon the earth; and ſo own <hi>the Croſs, and deſpiſe the ſhame,</hi> and give up your ſelves to ſuffer for the truth received, all you that would follow the <hi>Lamb</hi> to the <hi>Land of reſt,</hi> and through many trials you wil wax ſtrong and bold, and confident in your God; for God is not known what a God he is, until the time of tryal; and all keep your meetings in the name and fear of the <hi>Lord God,</hi> waiting for his power, in the obedience to his <hi>Light,</hi> which in your <hi>conſciences</hi> doth reprove you when you do amiſs, that in it you may wait, and watch over the <hi>foes</hi> that are of your own houſe, that you may know the <hi>warfare</hi> begun in your hearts againſt your ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al enemies; and ſo the <hi>God of Power</hi> manifeſt himſelf amongſt you by his mighty power, bringing down all that in you which oppoſes him, &amp; would not that he ſhould reign over it, and exalt his own ſeed in your hearts, &amp; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh you in <hi>righteouſneſs,</hi> that his image you may bear, and <hi>he ſhal be your God, and you ſhal be his people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And ſo in the unchangeable Truth, I reſt in unity with all the faithful in the glorious liberty of the Sons of God, though in outward bonds for your ſakes.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Known to all that can read me in ſpirit, I.P.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
